<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rss version="2.0"
  xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
  xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
  xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss">

  <channel>
    <title>
      <![CDATA[  Jacob Vaverka  ]]>
    </title>
    <link> https://jvaverka.github.io </link>
    <description>
      <![CDATA[  Where I write about math, code, and more.  ]]>
    </description>
    <atom:link
      href="https://jvaverka.github.io/feed.xml"
      rel="self"
      type="application/rss+xml" />


<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Packages Versus Projects in Julia  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jvaverka.github.io/posts/packages-versus-projects-in-julia/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jvaverka.github.io/posts/packages-versus-projects-in-julia/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  The Julia ecosystem has Packages &amp; Projects. This short guide attempts to help beginners get started with both.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<div class="tag"><i class="fa fa-tag"></i><a href="https://jvaverka.github.io/tag/code/">code</a>, <a href="https://jvaverka.github.io/tag/julia/">julia</a></div>
<h2 id="packages_versus_projects_in_julia">Packages Versus Projects in Julia</h2>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>Packages Versus Projects in Julia<ol><li>Pkg.jl</li><li>What is a Package?</li><li>What is a Project?</li></ol></li></ol></div>
<h3 id="pkgjl">Pkg.jl</h3>
<p>One of Julia&#39;s greatest strengths is its package manager, <code>Pkg.jl</code>. My goal here is to give new Julia users some helpful tips to get the most out of <code>Pkg.jl</code> right off the bat. To dive deeper, please check out the <a href="https://pkgdocs.julialang.org/v1/">official documentation</a>.</p>
<h3 id="what_is_a_package">What is a Package?</h3>
<p>A package is a code base that performs some function. I.e., a package does a job, does it well, and nothing more. It is modular.</p>
<p>When multiple things need to be done, we sensibly organize the appropriate code into separate packages. Furthermore, we give these separate packages separate names so that we can understand what job they do well.</p>
<p>Say you want to work with Hyper Text Markup Language &#40;HTML&#41;. <code>HTTP.jl</code> can help send requests and read responses.</p>
<p>Say you want to work with JavaScript Object Notation &#40;JSON&#41;. <code>JSON3.jl</code> can help read and write data in this format.</p>
<p>Say you want to fetch random XKCD comic &#40;there is no meaning&#41;. <code>XKCD.jl</code> can deliver comics to you. The beautiful thing is, that it does so by using <code>HTTP.jl</code> in combination with <code>JSON3.jl</code>.</p>
<p>Packages are the building blocks of the Julia ecosystem. There are many great packages out there, and the ease of creating, distributing, and composing packages allows the ecosystem to rapidly grow.</p>
<p>Those interested in building and sharing their own Julia package should leverage <a href="https://invenia.github.io/PkgTemplates.jl/stable/">PkgTemplates.jl</a> to save time and minimize common mistakes.</p>
<h3 id="what_is_a_project">What is a Project?</h3>
<p>A project is what you create to do stuff.</p>
<p>Slightly more formally, a project is any Julia code base with its own environment. In general, it is always a good idea to create an new environment for new projects. This will minimize the chances of package conflicts. Luckily, creating a new project with a dedicated environment is easy to do. We&#39;ll quickly walk through the steps to create a new project named <code>ImportantWork</code>.</p>
<p>After you have fired up a Julia REPL, indicate that we&#39;ll be using the package manager &#40;we&#39;ll focus only on the most idiomatic way of doing this for now, but there is a <code>Pkg</code> REPL mode accessible with <code>&#93;</code> detailed in the official docs&#41;.</p>
<pre><code class="language-julia-repl">julia&gt; using Pkg</code></pre>
<p>Now to create our project.</p>
<pre><code class="language-julia-repl">julia&gt; Pkg.generate&#40;&quot;ImportantWork&quot;&#41;</code></pre>
<p>The output looks something like this:</p>
<pre><code class="language-text">Generating  project ImportantWork:
    ImportantWork/Project.toml
    ImportantWork/src/ImportantWork.jl
Dict&#123;String, Base.UUID&#125; with 1 entry:
  &quot;ImportantWork&quot; &#61;&gt; UUID&#40;&quot;4b610261-c434-4966-b823-52987c24b398&quot;&#41;</code></pre>
<p>The Julia package manager just generated:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>a directory, <code>ImportantWork</code> ⇒ where everything for the project lives</p>
</li>
<li><p>a subdirectory, <code>ImportantWork/src</code> ⇒ for building our code base</p>
</li>
<li><p>a file, <code>ImportantWork/src/ImportantWork.jl</code> ⇒ a module &#40;think <code>main</code>&#41;</p>
</li>
<li><p>a file, <code>ImportantWork/Project.toml</code> ⇒ for describing the environment</p>
</li>
<li><p>a UUID we won&#39;t worry about for now</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Let&#39;s step into our new project with <code>cd</code>.</p>
<pre><code class="language-julia-repl">julia&gt; cd&#40;&quot;ImportantWork&quot;&#41;</code></pre>
<p>And check out <code>Project.toml</code>.</p>
<pre><code class="language-julia-repl">julia&gt; edit&#40;&quot;Project.toml&quot;&#41;</code></pre>
<p>The file contains some basic information about the project&#39;s environment.</p>
<pre><code class="language-text">name &#61; &quot;ImportantWork&quot;
uuid &#61; &quot;4b610261-c434-4966-b823-52987c24b398&quot;
authors &#61; &#91;&quot;Your Name &lt;you@example.com&gt;&quot;&#93;
version &#61; &quot;0.1.0&quot;</code></pre>
<p>To begin working with this new environment, simply activate it.</p>
<pre><code class="language-julia-repl">julia&gt; Pkg.activate&#40;&quot;.&quot;&#41;  # the . here means &#39;this directory&#39;</code></pre>
<p>Now we can continue to the important project work. To do so, we&#39;ll need the important <code>XKCD.jl</code> package. So let&#39;s add it to the project.</p>
<pre><code class="language-julia-repl">julia&gt; Pkg.add&#40;&quot;XKCD&quot;&#41;</code></pre>
<pre><code class="language-text">Updating registry at &#96;~/.julia/registries/General&#96;
   Resolving package versions...
    Updating &#96;~/Repos/ImportantWork/Project.toml&#96;
  &#91;4bc7fa8b&#93; &#43; XKCD v1.0.1
    Updating &#96;~/Repos/ImportantWork/Manifest.toml&#96;
  &#91;cd3eb016&#93; &#43; HTTP v0.9.17
  &#91;83e8ac13&#93; &#43; IniFile v0.5.0
  &#91;0f8b85d8&#93; &#43; JSON3 v1.9.2
  &#91;739be429&#93; &#43; MbedTLS v1.0.3
  &#91;69de0a69&#93; &#43; Parsers v2.2.0
  ...
  &#91;8dfed614&#93; &#43; Test
  &#91;cf7118a7&#93; &#43; UUIDs
  &#91;4ec0a83e&#93; &#43; Unicode
  &#91;c8ffd9c3&#93; &#43; MbedTLS_jll
Precompiling project...
  1 dependency successfully precompiled in 1 seconds &#40;9 already precompiled&#41;</code></pre>
<p>The <code>Project.toml</code> can again tell us what changed. There are 2 new lines.</p>
<pre><code class="language-text">&#91;deps&#93;
XKCD &#61; &quot;4bc7fa8b-4ef2-4643-8c8b-cef036f85839&quot;</code></pre>
<p>Indicating that our project has a new dependency.</p>
<p>We are now free to use the package in our project.</p>
<pre><code class="language-julia-repl">julia&gt; edit&#40;&quot;src/ImportantWork.jl&quot;&#41;</code></pre>
<p>Paste the following code in the file. Save and quit.</p>
<pre><code class="language-julia">module ImportantWorkusing XKCDexport meaning_of_life
export life_onlinemeaning_of_life&#40;&#41; &#61; XKCD.Comic&#40;42&#41;
life_online&#40;&#41; &#61; XKCD.Comic&#40;256&#41;end # module</code></pre>
<p>Finally, we can get the answers we seek. Furthermore, if we are sure to include the <code>Project.toml</code> then we can share our important work with others. Then they too can get the answers.</p>
<pre><code class="language-julia-repl">julia&gt; using ImportantWork
julia&gt; meaning_of_life&#40;&#41;</code></pre>
<p><img src="./geico.jpg" alt="geico" /></p>
<pre><code class="language-julia-repl">julia&gt; life_online&#40;&#41;</code></pre>
<p><img src="./online_communities.png" alt="online-communities" /></p>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Vaverka</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  Free As In Beer  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jvaverka.github.io/posts/free-as-in-beer/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jvaverka.github.io/posts/free-as-in-beer/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  My take on Linux and who it&#39;s for.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<div class="tag"><i class="fa fa-tag"></i><a href="https://jvaverka.github.io/tag/life/">life</a>, <a href="https://jvaverka.github.io/tag/linux/">linux</a></div>
<h2 id="free_as_in_beer">Free As In Beer</h2>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>Free As In Beer<ol><li>Free Beer?</li><li>GNU / Linux</li><li>Bad News<ol><li>Dependency Hell</li></ol></li><li>Good News<ol><li>Perfect Fit</li></ol></li></ol></li><li>Conclusion<ol><li>References</li></ol></li></ol></div>
<h3 id="free_beer">Free Beer?</h3>
<p>Things can be free, as in beer<sup id="fnref:free">[1]</sup>, as in costs no money. Or things can be free, as in speech, as in do whatever you want just leave me out of it. Linux is the shining example of both.</p>
<h3 id="gnu_linux">GNU / Linux</h3>
<p>Linux &#40;or GNU/Linux&#41; is a free and open-source operating system that I started using around 2018. Actually, my first encounter was in 2016, but I was a mere philistine who couldn&#39;t comprehend its relevance. Not coincidentally, re-introduction corresponded with my joining a high-powered development team. Embracing Linux &#40;and open-source software in general&#41; revealed a new perspective on what was possible on computers.</p>
<p>However, there is some good news and some bad news. Such is life.</p>
<h3 id="bad_news">Bad News</h3>
<p>There is an old adage:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Linux is only free if your time has no value.<sup id="fnref:linux">[2]</sup></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I.e., prepare yourself for a time-sink.</p>
<p>I believe most Linux users would concede this point.<sup id="fnref:but">[3]</sup> The learning curve is real, it can be steep, and only the committed among us survive the journey to reap the reward.</p>
<p>While we&#39;re at it, let&#39;s gripe a bit:</p>
<p>🍇 Terminals are scary &#40;at first&#41;<sup id="fnref:term">[4]</sup></p>
<p>🍇 Hardware support not guaranteed &#42;cough&#42; GPUs &amp; Bluetooth</p>
<p>🍇 Foot-guns are a thing</p>
<p>What&#39;s a <em>foot-gun</em> you ask. Let me demonstrate.</p>
<h4 id="dependency_hell">Dependency Hell</h4>
<p><img src="./world-of-pain.jpg" alt="world-of-pain" /></p>
<p>Ever heard of <a href="https://harfbuzz.github.io/"><code>harfbuzz</code></a>? Me neither until I thought ligatures were a real terminal necessity. Don&#39;t know what ligatures are? Maybe your better off not knowing.<sup id="fnref:jk">[5]</sup> Gross over simplification - <code>harfbuzz</code> is a library needed for ligatures. No problem - there&#39;s a build section in the library docs, and after my first <code>meson build</code> I have my ligatures&#33;</p>
<p>I&#39;m pretty pleased until some time later upon realizing that several other programs depend on this library and are now failing. One solution proposed on Arch Wiki was to set the <code>LD_PRELOAD</code> environment variable to help each program find its preferred library. Kind of a hack-y band aid, but it got me unstuck and working again. &quot;Flipping&quot; this additional switch was fine until I ran across programs that failed no matter which way the switch was flipped. Finally, I was forced to confront the real problem.</p>
<p>The solution - do another <code>meson build</code> with an additional flag that was needed for my particular system and which was not well documented. This was painful. When you&#39;re navigating uncharted waters, it&#39;s unclear where the danger will be lurking. However, that does <em>NOT</em> mean that you should be scared to explore. This bout frustrated me at times, but I learned about <code>harfbuzz</code> and why programs like <code>Libre Office</code> and <code>Pandoc</code> rely on it.</p>
<p>Anyone who gets started with Linux will find their own unique <em><em>Harfbuzz Hell</em></em> because each user will customize their machine to their liking for their functions. So best advise is embrace it and look for the learning opportunities. They are plentiful.</p>
<h3 id="good_news">Good News</h3>
<p>Congratulations for making it to the good news &#40;we&#39;re almost done here&#41;. In keeping with the theme, here is another obscure quote.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>To live only for some future goal is shallow. It&#39;s the sides of the mountain which sustain life, not the top. Here&#39;s where things grow.<sup id="fnref:zen">[6]</sup></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Diving into the unknown and keeping an open mind will reveal many treasures among the growing pains. There is a lot to explore. So many brilliant people have worked hard on open-source projects and selflessly shared the end product. There&#39;s really no <em>need</em> to pay for an operating system or any software if you don&#39;t want to. A little exploration will prove this, and those things which seemed scary will turn out to be over-sized teddy bears.</p>
<p>There&#39;s too many to count, but here are some things I appreciate:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>💙 Terminals ⇒ beautifully simple command line tools<sup id="fnref:cli">[7]</sup></p>
</li>
<li><p>💙 Open-source ⇒ constant innovations</p>
</li>
<li><p>💙 Shell ⇒ script automate everything</p>
</li>
<li><p>💙 Options ⇒ for those who want better</p>
</li>
<li><p>💙 Freedom &#40;as in speech&#41; ⇒ customize everything<sup id="fnref:de">[8]</sup></p>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="perfect_fit">Perfect Fit</h4>
<p>Every person has different need, use-case, aesthetic, etc. It follows that every person has a different <em>perfect</em> computer setup. Just like how the world is not black and white, not everyone can be fully described in one of two buckets.<sup id="fnref:os">[9]</sup></p>
<p>There is a richness in diversity in Linux. Users have a choice of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linux_distribution">distribution</a> suited for particular purposes and tastes &#40;maybe too many choices so just pick <a href="https://ubuntu.com/">Ubuntu</a> to start then <a href="https://embeddedinventor.com/distro-hopping-what-why-how-explained/">hop</a> to your desire&#41;. Users have a choice of <a href="https://itsfoss.com/what-is-desktop-environment/">desktop environment</a> that will help them fine tune the look and feel that works best for them. Finally, users have full control of their systems. Users can do <em>anything</em> and are only limited by the time they choose invest.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p><img src="./opinion.jpg" alt="opinion" /></p>
<p>Good software exists. Some of it&#39;s free-as-in-beer, some of it&#39;s free-as-in-speech. There&#39;s many cases of both throughout Linux and the wider Open-source community. Best part - it&#39;s for everybody&#33;</p>
<p>Remember, you are not alone. There is a strong community of Linux enthusiasts in the world who are willing and able to help you get started. Anyone can do this and there is nothing to lose.</p>
<p>Linux &#40;and Open-source software in general&#41; is a bountiful garden. Dig it.</p>
<p>Share this with a curious soul or anyone asking about Linux.</p>
<h3 id="references">References</h3>
<p><table class="fndef" id="fndef:free">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[1]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gratis_versus_libre">Gratis versus libre</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:linux">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[2]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://www.brainyquote.com/quotes/jamie_zawinski_320496">Jamie Zawinski</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:but">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[3]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">See the <a href="https://jvaverka.github.io/posts/free-as-in-beer#good_news">Good News</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:term">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[4]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">You learn to love them. As I write this there are 8 on my system.</td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:jk">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[5]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">Just kidding, they&#39;re awesome ⇒ ⇗ ⇑ ⇖ ⇐ ⇙ ⇓ ⇘ ⇒ α ≥ β ≤ γ ≠ δ ⬖</td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:zen">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[6]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content">From <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/629.Zen_and_the_Art_of_Motorcycle_Maintenance">Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:cli">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[7]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://github.com/agarrharr/awesome-cli-apps">awesome-cli-apps</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:de">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[8]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://itsfoss.com/best-linux-desktop-environments/">Desktop Environments</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
<table class="fndef" id="fndef:os">
    <tr>
        <td class="fndef-backref">[9]</td>
        <td class="fndef-content"><a href="https://gs.statcounter.com/os-market-share/desktop/worldwide/#monthly-202012-202112">Global Desktop Operating System Market Share</a></td>
    </tr>
</table>
</p>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Vaverka</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>

<item>
  <title>
    <![CDATA[  My Julia Story  ]]>
  </title>
  <link> https://jvaverka.github.io/posts/my-julia-story/index.html </link>
  <guid> https://jvaverka.github.io/posts/my-julia-story/index.html </guid>
  <description>
    <![CDATA[  The path I traveled through academia and industry that lead me to Julia.  ]]>
  </description>  
  
  <content:encoded>
    <![CDATA[  
<div class="tag"><i class="fa fa-tag"></i><a href="https://jvaverka.github.io/tag/julia/">julia</a>, <a href="https://jvaverka.github.io/tag/life/">life</a></div>
<h2 id="my_julia_story">My Julia Story</h2>
<div class="franklin-toc"><ol><li>My Julia Story<ol><li>Origins</li><li>Adoption</li><li>Arrival</li></ol></li><li>Resources<ol><li>Julia Programming Language</li><li>Applied Linear Algebra</li></ol></li></ol></div>
<h3 id="origins">Origins</h3>
<p>In 2019 I was living in Detroit and experiencing the coldest winter of my life - we&#39;re talking <strong>subzero for two weeks</strong> straight, cold. During the day I was programming software to run Computational Fluid Dynamics simulations on a High Performance Compute environment. At night I was continuing my education in Applied Mathematics by taking a course in Matrix Theory. Mostly, I was just trying to stay warm. Overall, things were going well. I was leveling up my software development game and even got to use my math degree from time to time on some projects. Little did I know things were only going to get better.</p>
<p>My Matrix Theory professor, let&#39;s call him <em>Professor</em>, was the best. He allowed students to use their preferred programming language for computation, but he recommended we consider using a new language called <strong>Julia</strong>. According to Professor, Julia was really an up and coming language, and for the first few assignments Professor challenged the MATLAB, Python, and R users to match the speed and expressiveness achieved by Julia. The results were impressive, and I was sold. Before long, I was hooked.</p>
<h3 id="adoption">Adoption</h3>
<p>After my coursework I fought to get Julia a foothold my industry. My team at work was a shining example of a group suffering from <a href="https://youtu.be/qGW0GT1rCvs">the two language problem</a>. We had brilliant engineers and talented software developers. Sure, we were productive, but I wanted to help us work smarter, develop faster, and build more impactful tools. With Julia, I felt I had just the thing.</p>
<p>My best bet was to become the Julia champion. So for the next 1½ years, my free time was spent researching the language, the ecosystem, the tooling, everything. I had a new hobby, and soon I became &quot;the Julia guy&quot; in the office.</p>
<h3 id="arrival">Arrival</h3>
<p>The deeper I looked the more rewarding the experience. I joined the community Discourse, Discord, Slack, Zulip, etc. You name it, I was there. I loved finding out what folks were able to build with Julia. Even cooler, I found out that this community of Julians was made up of kind, smart, and diverse people living all over the world.</p>
<p>While I was hoping to champion Julia from within my company, I didn&#39;t wait to begin making small contributions. I started building fun web dashboards with <code>Dash.jl</code>, helpful study materials with <code>Symbolics.jl</code>, this blog with <code>Franklin.jl</code>, and even helped &#40;a <em>tiny</em> bit&#41; support <code>LanguageServer.jl</code> in <a href="https://www.lunarvim.org/languages/julia.html#julia">LunarVim</a>. After gaining some confidence I was able to help other newcomers by pointing out useful Packages and improving documentation.</p>
<p>All the time invested in Julia paid off in the unexpected form of a job offer. I can happily say that my favorite hobby is now also my day job&#33; So if you are at all curious about this ambitious, <a href="https://julialang.org/blog/2012/02/why-we-created-julia/">greedy</a>, new language called Julia, then I would encourage you to join the community.  I found my dream job. Who knows what you&#39;ll discover.</p>
<p>Thank you to all Julians who helped me get started and encouraged me to keep exploring 🙏</p>
<h2 id="resources">Resources</h2>
<p>In case you are interested in learning more about the Julia Programming Language or Applied Linear Algebra, here are some resources that helped me on my journey.</p>
<h3 id="julia_programming_language">Julia Programming Language</h3>
<p>Instructions for joining the many community channels can be found on the <a href="https://julialang.org/community/">community</a> page of the official <a href="https://julialang.org/">Julia Lang</a> website.</p>
<p>Wondering if Julia is a good choice for you and your projects? Start by reading <a href="https://juliadatascience.io/julia_accomplish">What Julia Aims to Accomplish</a>.</p>
<h3 id="applied_linear_algebra">Applied Linear Algebra</h3>
<p>My Matrix Theory course was taught with two complementary books:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://www.maa.org/press/maa-reviews/applied-linear-algebra">Applied Linear      Algebra</a>      primarily focuses on theory</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://web.stanford.edu/~boyd/vmls/">Introduction to Applied Linear Algebra – Vectors, Matrices, and Least      Squares</a> &#40;VMLS for short&#41; focus      more on application of the subject matter</p>
</li>
</ul>
 ]]>
  </content:encoded>
    
  <pubDate>Sat, 18 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>  
  
  
  <atom:author>
    <atom:name>Jacob Vaverka</atom:name>
  </atom:author>
        
</item>
</channel></rss>